

Edward Whitehead

Current Role: Software Developer

Date / Place of Birth: 21/06/1973 / Johannesburg

Ideal Role: Development Manager

Nationality: South African Address: Moscow, Russia Willing to Relocate: Yes Email: ed.surreal@gmail.com

Driving License: Yes

Remote Work: Preferred Mobile: +27 (0)76-797-5137 Mobile: +7-985-084-0676

Dependants: 2

Marital Status: Married Languages: English, Afrikaans

<u>LinkedIn</u> | <u>GitHub</u>

Profile

Edward is the Founder and owner of PayBee[™], a payment processing solution currently in development. The techstack he uses is primarily Google products namely Flutter, Dart and Firebase.

Over the past three years, he has worked remotely in different countries, developing on a range of platforms as a Subject Matter Expert, Senior Software Developer, Team Lead and Architect.

At Bumblebee Consulting he was a Senior Software Developer/Team Lead for a couple years, focusing on Ionic, Xamarin, API and Azure development. He also played a role as subject matter expert for a mobile broker solution that was developed in Xamarin and he implemented Bumblebee's CICD pipelines in Azure using YAML.

At FedEx, Edward spent nine years as a Senior Application Developer and Mobile Software Architect, specifically as the lead for the mobile stack (front end/back-end), nationally across South Africa.

Tech-Stack

C#, Xamarin Forms, Flutter, Dart, .Net 4.x – 6.x, Standard, Core, Visual Studio, Visual Studio Code, GitHub, Azure DevOps, Azure Pipelines (YAML), AppCenter, CodeMagic, JavaScript, TypeScript, Angular, Ionic, HTML, CSS, Restful/Web API, Figma (UI), Flutterflow, Solidity, web3

Soft Skills

General Management, IT Lead, Team Lead, Project Lead, Mentoring, Coaching, Project Management, IT Dev. Policies & Procedures, IT Dev. Coding Standards & Guidelines, Technical Documentation, Human Resource Management, Performance Management, Financial Management, Marketing, Vendor Management, Supplier Management, Solution Architecture, Event Management, Sponsorship Management.

Education

Signa - N4 General Management - 2016

Johannesburg Technical College – Mathematics, Technical Drawing, Theory, Science – 1993

Udemy – Flutter & Dart – The Complete Guide – 2020

Udemy – Qt 6 Core Beginners with C++ - 2021

Udemy – Ethereum Blockchain Developer Bootcamp With Solidity – 2022

Udemy - Complete C# Masterclass

Employment History

Contracting, Remote

Software Developer December 2021 – Current

Client: SmartTask

- Initially contracted for the company for approximately twelve months.
- Did an in-depth review of their Xamarin Forms application before beginning with the process of upgrading the solution to the latest Xamarin platform and ensuring the ability to target the latest

- operating system versions for Android and iOS.
- Successfully upgraded the solution and now resolving issues and performing additional enhancements to the application and solution.

Noteworthy Achievements:

Successfully upgraded the solution that allowed the company to target the latest platform version for Android and iOS, given they could no longer release any further versions to the stores as result of a redundant solution.

Client: Thinkology

- Took over the implementation of a mobile application that was to be used in the beauty industry by IIAA. The end goal of the application was to capture client details after which, the clients would have headshot photos of themselves processed to eventually provide recommendations about what beauty products to use.
- Development efforts included implementation of NFC, refactoring code to follow the MVVM pattern and fix the complex problems that were already in place. The refactoring of the code also saw notable improvements in the user interface, that were constantly delayed or causing the application to hang and crash on a regular basis.
- At times, there were two to three releases of the application per day.

AZ Consulting, Remote, Contract

Senior Software Developer March 2021 – April 2022

- Senior software developer where I performed architectural reviews as a subject matter expert.
- Performed solution upgrades in Xamarin for clients in the United Kingdom and South Africa.
- Conducted technical interviews to ensure the correct fit for client's requirements.
- Primary focus was mobile using Xamarin.

Payment Bee Inc., Remote

Founder

August 2021 - Current

- Fintech company offering a unique service to process gratuity and currently aimed at the restaurant industry globally.
- Future scope includes creating a fully-fledged payment processing gateway to extend the services offered.

Bumblebee Cape Town, Remote

Senior Software Developer/Team Lead October 2019 – September 2021

- Past projects included being a Team Lead for a group of developers for a contract client in the insurance industry.
- Developing cloud-based insurance solution in .Net Core, Angular and Azure.
- Implemented DevOps pipelines in Azure using YAML.
- Agile Methodologies Development.
- Team Lead for a team of junior to intermediate developers for the upgrade of MobeeWash, an on-demand mobile car wash booking system.
- Subject matter expert to corporate clients, offering advice on architecture patterns used in software solutions and what upgrades were required to ensure up-to-date systems.

iOCO Cape Town, South Africa, Contract Senior Software Developer April 2019 – October 2019

Outsourced to corporate clients.

- Team Lead for new in-house mobile application for an insurance company (Sanlam).
- Developed a Progressive Web Application and deployed to Android and iOS using Capacitor.
- Agile Methodologies Development.
- Development of responsive web, native and hybrid mobile applications.
- Solution Architecture for the mobile and web application stack.

Noteworthy Achievements:

Successfully completed the first mobile application for the division within the company within two sprints.

Career Break, Johannesburg, South Africa Career Break January 2018 – March 2019

- In December 2017, I took a sabbatical from my career in the information technology field.
- I ran my own event company and gained valuable soft skills as director of my company and through this process also learned, that for me to be successful in a career within information technology sector, I must focus on a role that will afford me an opportunity to lead teams.
- I decided to return to the information technology sector, was because I love technology and I would love the opportunity to be a creative visionary and the leader of a development team.
- During my sabbatical I gained the following experience: Project Management, Vendor Management, Floor Planning, Financial Management, Sponsorship Proposals and Management, Digital Marketing, Graphic Design (Canva), Supplier Management, HR/Staff Management.
- I also gained knowledge in Angular, .Net Core, Entity Framework Core and ASP.Net Core WebApi.

Noteworthy Achievements:

Secured the contract to provide food and beverage services to public and staff for Comic Con Africa, 2018. Successfully held over fifteen events within the calendar year.

FedEx, Johannesburg, South Africa Mobile Software Architect, Application Developer – Senior June 2010 – March 2018

- Team Lead for several projects, primarily in mobile and customs clearance.
- IT Lead for Mobility and Customs Clearance (Southern Africa).
- Responsible for the migration of legacy customs clearance system to cloud based solution (SaaS).
- Software/Solution Architecture for mobile and web application stack.
- Responsible for implementing N-tier mobile application and assisted in the solution framework for the core operating system within FedEx, South Africa.
- Application increased data transmission between client and server by up to 200% and was completely
 developed in C#/WCF.
 Lead the upgrading of current legacy customs clearance solution to a cloud-based
 solution.
- Provided limited SharePoint Administration within the company and would oversee certain aspects of the organisation's intranet.
- Vendor Management Responsible for overseeing project to port legacy mobile application from Windows Mobile to Xamarin.
- Software Development Core developer for the legacy mobile platform for FedEx Southern Africa.

Noteworthy Achievements:

Having re-developed and launched the courier application as part of my duties at FedEx, the application set a standard that would eventually see the software being upgraded and ported over to Android in the last couple of years at FedEx.

The implementation of the new software when starting, was to simply upgrade the application to a newer platform, but the result was an application that implemented zip compression technology on both client and server that saw data transfer rates improve by up to 200% as well as a new architecture being implemented

that required minimal maintenance.

Various, Johannesburg, South Africa, Software Developer, March 2007 – May 2010
African Access Holdings, Kwa-Zulu Natal, South Africa, IT Manager, March 2006 – January 2007
Metrofile, Johannesburg, South Africa, Webmaster, Product Specialist Sep 2002 – Nov 2005
Various, Johannesburg, South Africa, Computer Trainer Mar 2001 – Aug 2002
New Horizons, Johannesburg, South Africa, Account Executive Jun 1999 – Feb 2001
Autopage Cellular, Johannesburg, South Africa, Client Liaison Jan 1998 – May 1999
Tejloy Cellular, Johannesburg, South Africa, Client Liaison Jun 1995 – Dec 1997

Reference Materials

- Kirsten An app that will be developed as a dedication to my daughter who was painfully taken from me in 2020: https://bit.ly/3HfTVtq
- PayBee A product currently in development within the FinTech space: https://bit.ly/3QfU5oN
- MobeeWash An on-demand wash washing service that is live on the stores. I was senior developer/Team
 Lead for this internal project at Bumblebee: https://bit.ly/3QhuBay
- MobeeWash another version of the same app, but slightly difference design: https://bit.ly/30fE40t